<?xml version="1.0"?>

<extracts xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hakluyt_schema.xsd">
  <extract id="E001">
    <title>
      The first Voyage of <person>M. Martine Frobisher</person>, to the Northwest, for the search of the straight or passage to <place>China</place>, written by <person>Christopher Hall</person>, Master in the <ship>Gabriel</ship>, and made in the yeere of our Lord 1576.
    </title>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-06-07">The 7. of Iune being Thursday</date>, the two Barks, viz. the <ship>Gabriel</ship>, and the
      <ship>Michael</ship> <note>M. Matthew Kinderslye was Captaine of the Michael.</note>
      and our Pinnesse set saile at <place>Ratcliffe</place>, and bare down to <place>Detford</place>, and
      there we ancred: the cause was that our Pinnesse burst her boulsprit, and
      foremast aboard of a ship that rode at <place>Detford</place>, else wee meant to haue past
      that day by the Court then at <place>Grenewich</place>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <date date="1576-06-08">8. day being Friday</date>, about 12 of the clocke we wayed at <place>Detford</place>, and
      set saile all three of vs, and bare downe by the Court, where we shotte off
      our ordinance and made the best shew we could: <person>Her Maiestie</person> beholding the
      same, commended it, and bade vs farewell, with shaking her hand at vs out
      of the window. Afterward shee sent <person>a Gentleman</person> aboord of vs, who declared
      that <person>her Maiestie</person> had good liking of our doings, and thanked vs for it, and
      also willed <person>our Captaine</person> to come the next day to the Court to take his
      leaue of her.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-06-08">The same day</date> towards night <person>M. Secretarie Woolly</person> came aboorde of vs, and
      declared to the company, that <person>her Maiestie</person> had appointed him to giue them
      charge to be obedient, and diligent to <person>their Captaine</person>, and gouernours in
      all things, and wished vs happie successe.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <date date="1576-06-12">12. day</date> being ouer against <place>Grauesend</place>, by the castle or blockehouse, we
      obserued the latitude, which was 51. degrees 33. min. And in that place the
      variation of the Compasse is 11. degrees and a halfe.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>Faire Island.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-06-24">24. day</date> at 2. of the clocke after noone, I
      had sight of <place>Faire yle</place>, being from vs 6. leagues North and by East, and
      when I brought it Northwest and by North, it did rise at the Southermost
      ende with a litle hommocke, and swampe in the middes.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>Shotland.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-06-25">25. day</date> from 4. to 8. a clocke in the forenoone,
      the winde at Northwest and by North a fresh gale, I cast about to the
      Westward, <place>the Southermost head of Shotland called Swinborne head</place>
      Northnorthwest from me, and the land of <place>Faire yle</place>, West Southwest from me.
      I sailed directly to the North head of that said land, sounding as I ranne
      in, hauing 60. 50. and 40. fathoms, and gray redde shels: and within halfe
      a mile of that Island, there are 36. fathoms, for I sailed to that Island
      to see whether there were any roadesteede for a Northwest winde, and I
      found by my sounding hard rockes, and foule ground, and deepe water, within
      two cables length of the shoare, 28. fathome, and so did not ancre but
      plied to and fro with my foresaile, and mizen till it was a high water
      vnder the Island. The tide setteth there Northwest and Southeast: the flood
      setteth Southeast, and the ebbe Northwest.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <date date="1576-06-26">26. day</date> hauing the winde at South a faire gale, sayling from <place>Faire yle</place>
      to <place>Swinborne head</place>, I did obserue the latitude, the <place>Island of Fowlay</place> being
      West Northwest from me 6. leagues, and <place>Swinborne head</place> East southeast from
      me, I found my eleuation <note>By eleuation he meaneth the
      distance of the sunne from the zenith.</note> to be 37. degr and my declination
      22. degr. 46 min. So that my latitude was 59. degr. 46. min. <sidenote>S.
      Tronions.</sidenote> At that present being neere to <place>Swinborne head</place>, hauing a leake
      which did trouble vs, as also to take in fresh water, I plyed roome with a
      sound, which is called <place>S. Tronions</place>, and there did ancre in seuen fathoms
      water, and faire sande. You haue comming in the sounds mouth in the entring
      17. 15. 12. 10. 9. 8. and 7. fathoms, and the sound lyeth in North
      northwest, and there we roade to a West sunne, and stopped our leake, and
      hauing refreshed our selues with water, at a North northwest sunne, I set
      saile from <place>S. Tronions</place> the winde at South Southest, and turned out till wee
      were cleare of the sound, and so sailed West to go cleare of the <place>Island of
      Fowlay</place>. <sidenote>Fowlay Island.</sidenote> And running off toward <place>Fowlay</place>, I
      sounded, hauing fiftie fathome, and streamie ground, and also I sounded
      <place>Fowlay</place> being North from mee one league off that Islande, hauing fiftie
      fathome at the South head, and streamie ground, like broken otmell, and one
      shell being redde and white like mackerell.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>Latitude 59. deg. 59. min. Here they begin to saile West and by
      North.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-06-27">27. day</date> at a South sunne I did obserue the latitude, the <place>Island
      of Fowlay</place> being from me two leagues East Northeast: I found my selfe to be
      in latitude 59. degrees, 59. min truly obserued, the winde at South
      Southwest: I sailed West and by North.
    </para>

    <para>
      From 12. to foure a clocke afternoone, the wind at South, a faire gale the
      shippe sailed West and by North 6. leagues, and at the ende of this watch,
      I sounded hauing 60. fathome, with little stones and shels, <place>the Island</place> from
      vs 8. leagues East.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>July the first.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-07-01">first of Iuly</date>, from 4. to 8. a clocke, wee
      sailed West 4. glasses 4. leagues, and at that present we had so much winde
      that we spooned afore the sea Southwest 2. leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      The 3. day we found our Compasse to bee varied one point to Westwards: this
      day from 4. to 8. a clocke we sailed West and by North 6 leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      From 8. to 12. a clocke at noone West and by North 4. leagues.
      <sidenote>The Compasse varying Westwards one point.</sidenote> At that present I found our
      compasse to be varied 11 deg. and one 4. part to the Westwards, which is
      one point.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>The Island of Friseland.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-07-11">11. day</date> at a Southeast sunne we
      had sight of <place>the land of Friseland</place> bearing from vs West northwest 16.
      leagues, and rising like pinacles of steeples, and all couered with snowe.
      I found my selfe in 61. degr. of latitude. Wee sailed to the shoare and
      could finde no ground at 150. fathoms, we hoised out our boate, and the
      Captaine with 4. men rowed to the shoare to get on land, but the land lying
      full of yce, they could not get on land, and so they came aboord againe: We
      had much adoe to get cleare of the yce by reason of the fogge. Yet from
      Thursday 8. a clocke in the morning to Friday at noone we sailed Southwest
      20. leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <date date="1576-07-18">18. day</date> at a Southwest sunne I found the sunne to be eleuated 33. deg.
      And at a Southsoutheast sunne 40. deg. So I obserued it till I found it at
      the highest, and then it was eleuated 52. deg. <sidenote>The variation of
      the needle two points and a halfe to the West.</sidenote> I iudged the variation of
      the Compasse to be 2. points and a halfe to the Westward.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>A great drift of yce.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-07-21">21. day</date> we had sight of a great drift
      of yce, seeming <place>a firme land</place>, and we cast Westward to be cleare of it.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>The latitude of 62. degrees 2. min.</sidenote> The 26. we had sight of a
      land of yce: the latitude was 62. degrees, and two minutes.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>Sight of land supposed to haue been Labrador.</sidenote> The <date date="1576-07-28">28. day</date> in
      the morning was very foggie: but at the clearing vp of the fogge, we had
      sight of lande, which I supposed to be <place>Labrador</place>, with great store of yce
      about the land: I ranne in towards it, and sownded, but could get no ground
      at 100. fathom, and the yce being so thicke, I could not get to the shoare,
      and so lay off, and came cleare of the yce. Upon Munday we came within a
      mile of the shoare, and sought a harborowe: all the sownd was full of yce,
      and our boate rowing a shoare, could get no ground at 100. fathom, within a
      Cables length of the shoare: then we sailed Eastnortheast along the shoare,
      for so the lande lyeth, and the currant is there great, setting Northeast,
      and Southwest: and if we could haue gotten anker ground, wee would haue
      seene with what force it had runne, but I iudge a ship may driue a league
      and a halfe, in one houre, with that tide.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-07-28">This day</date> at 4. of the clocke in the morning, being faire and cleere, we had
      sight of <place>a head land</place>, as we iudged, bearing from vs north, and by East, and
      we sailed Northeast, and by North to that land, and when we came thither,
      wee could not get to the lande for yce: for the yce stretched along the
      coast, so that we could not come to the land, by fiue leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>August.</sidenote> <date date="1576-08-01">Wednesday the first of August</date> it calmed, and in the
      after noone I caused my boate to be hoysed out, being hard by a great
      Island of yce, and I and foure men rowed to that yce, and sounded within
      two Cables length of it, and had sixteene fathome, and little stones, and
      after that sownded againe within a Minion shot, and had ground at an
      hundreth fathome, and faire sand: we sownded the next day a quarter of a
      myle from it, and had sixtie fathome rough ground, and at that present
      being aboord, that great Island of yce fell one part from another, making a
      noyse as if a great cliffe had fallen into the Sea. And at foure of the
      clocke I sownded againe, and had 90. fathome, and small blacke stones, and
      little white stones like pearles. The tide here did set to the shoare.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-10">The tenth</date> I tooke foure men, and my selfe, and rowed to
      shoare to <place>an Island</place> one league from the maine, and there the
      flood setteth Southwest alongest the shoare, and it floweth as
      neere as I could iudge so too, I could not tarry to prooue it,
      because the ship was a great way from me, and I feared a fogge:
      but when I came a shoare, it was a low water. I went to <place>the top
      of the Island</place>, and before I came backe, it was hied a foote water,
      and so without tarrying I came aboord.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>They enter the Streit in the latitude of 63. deg. and 8. min.</sidenote>
      <date date="1576-08-11">The 11.</date> we found our latitude to be 63. degr. and eight minutes, and this
      day we entred <place>the streight</place>.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-12">The 12.</date> wee set saile towardes an Island, called the <place>Gabriels Island</place>, which
      was 10 leagues then from vs.
    </para>

    <para>
      We espied a sound, and bare with it, and came to a <place>Sandie Baye</place>, where we
      came to an anker, the land being East southeast off vs, and there we rode
      al night in 8. fathome water. It floweth there at a Southeast Moone. We
      called it <place>Priors sownd</place>, being from the <place>Gabriels Island</place>, tenne leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-14">The 14</date>, we waied, and ranne into <place>another sownde</place>, where wee ankered in 8.
      fathome water, faire sand, and black oaze, and there calked our ship, being
      weake from the wales vpward, and tooke in fresh water.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-15">The 15. day</date> we waied, and sailed to Priors Bay, being a mile from thence.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-16">The 16. day</date> was calme, and we rode still, without yce, but presently within
      two houres it was frozen round about the ship, a quarter of an ynch thicke,
      and that day very faire, and calme.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-17">The 17. day</date> we waied, and came to <place>Thomas Williams Island</place>.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-18">The 18. day</date> we sailed North northwest, and ankered againe in
      23. fathome, and tough oaze, vnder <place>Burchers Island</place>, which is from
      <place>the former Island</place>, ten leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>Sight of the Countrey people.</sidenote> The 19. day in the morning, being
      calme, and no winde, <person>the Captaine</person> and <person>I</person> tooke our boat, with eight men in
      her, to rowe vs a shoare, to see if there were any people, or no, and going
      to <place>the toppe of the Island</place>, we had sight of seuen boates, which came rowing
      from the East side, toward <place>that Island</place>: whereupon we returned aboord
      againe: at length we sent our boate with fiue men in her, to see whither
      they rowed, and so with a white cloth brought one of their boates with
      their men along the shoare, rowing after our boate, till such time as they
      sawe our ship, and then they rowed a shoare: then I went on shore my selfe,
      and gaue euery of them a threadden point, and brought one of them aboord of
      me, where hee did eate and drinke, and then carried him on shoare againe.
      Whereupon all the rest came aboord with their boates, being nineteene
      persons, and they spake, but we vnderstoode them not. <sidenote>The
      description of the people.</sidenote> They bee like to Tartars, with long blacke
      haire, broad faces, and flatte noses, and tawnie in colour, wearing Seale
      skinnes, and so doe the women, not differing in the fashion, but the women
      are marked in the face with blewe streekes downe the cheekes, and round
      about the eyes. Their boates are made all of Seales skinnes, with a keele
      of wood within the skin: the proportion of them is like a Spanish shallop,
      saue only they be flat in the bottome, and sharpe at both ends.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-20">The twentieth day</date> wee wayed, and went to the Eastside of this island, and I
      and the Captaine, with foure men more went on shoare, and there we sawe
      their houses, and the people espying vs, came rowing towards our boate:
      whereupon we plied toward our boate: and wee being in our boate and they
      ashoare, they called to vs, and we rowed to them, and one of their company
      came into our boate, and we carried him a boord, and gaue him a Bell, and a
      knife: <sidenote>5 of our men taken by the people.</sidenote> so the Captaine and I
      willed fiue of our men to set him a shoare at a rocke, and not among the
      company, which they come from, but their wilfulnesse was such, that they
      would goe to them, and so were taken themselues, and our boate lost.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-21">The next day</date> in the morning, we stoode in neere the shoare, and shotte off
      a fauconet, and sounded our trumpet, but we could hear nothing nothing of
      our men: this sound wee called <place>the fiue mens sound</place>, and plyed out of it,
      but ankered againe in thirtie fathome, and ooze: and riding there all
      night, in the morning, the snow lay a foote thicke vpon our hatches.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-22">The 22. day</date> in the morning we wayed, and went againe to the place we lost
      our men, and our boate. We had sight of foureteene boates, and some came
      neere to vs, but wee could learne nothing of our men: among the rest, we
      intised one boate to our ships side, with a Bell, and in giuing him the
      Bell, we tooke him, and his boate, and so kept him, and so rowed downe to
      <place>Thomas Williams Island</place>, and there ankered all night.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>They returne.</sidenote> <date date="1576-08-26">The 26. day</date> we waied, to come homeward, and by
      12. of the clocke at noone, we were thwart of <place>Trumpets Island</place>.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-27">The next day</date> we came thwart of <place>Gabriels Island</place>, and at 8. of the clocke at
      night, we had the <place>Cape Labrador</place> as we supposed West from vs, ten leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-08-28">The 28. day</date> we went our course Southeast.
    </para>

    <para>
      We sailed Southeast, and by East, 22. leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-09-01">The first day of September</date> in the morning we had sight of the land of
      Friseland being eight leagues from vs but we could not come neerer it, for
      the monstrous yce that lay about it. From this day, till the sixth of this
      Moneth, we ranne along Island, and had the South part of it at eight of the
      clocke, East from vs ten leagues.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-09-07">The seuenth day of this moneth</date> we had a very terrible storme, by force
      whereof, <person>one of our men</person> was blowen into the sea out of our waste, but he
      caught hold of the foresaile sheate, and there held till <person>the Captaine</person>
      pluckt him againe into the ship.
    </para>

    <para>
      <date date="1576-09-25">The 25 day of this moneth</date> we had sight of the <place>Island of Orkney</place>, which was
      then East from vs.
    </para>

    <para>
      <sidenote>The Sheld.</sidenote> <date date="1576-10-01">The first day of October</date> we had sight of the Sheld,
      and so sailed about the coast, and ankered at <place>Yarmouth</place>, and the next day we
      came into <place>Harwich</place>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The language of the people of <place>Meta incognita</place>.
    </para>

    <list>
      Argoteyt, a hand.
      Cangnawe, a nose.
      Arered, an eye.
      Keiotot, a tooth.
      Mutchatet, the head.
      Chewat, an eare.
      Comagaye, a legge.
      Atoniagay, a foote.
      Callagay, a paire of breeches.
      Attegay, a coate.
      Polleuetagay, a knife.
      Accaskay, a shippe.
      Coblone, a thumbe.
      Teckkere, the foremost finger.
      Ketteckle, the middle finger.
      Mekellacane, the fourth finger.
      Yacketrone, the little finger.
    </list>
  </extract>

  <extract id="E002">
      <title>
        The second voyage of <person>Master Martin Frobisher</person>, made to the West and Northwest Regions, in the yeere 1577. with a description of the Countrey, and people: Written by <person>Master Dionise Settle</person>.
      </title>

      <para>
        On Whitsunday, being <date date="1577-05-26">the sixe and twentieth of May, in the yeere of our
        Lord God 1577</date>. <person>Captaine Frobisher</person> departed from <place>Blacke Wall</place>, with one of
        <person>the Queenes Maiesties</person> ships, called <ship>The Aide</ship>, of nine score tunnes, or
        thereabouts: and two other Little Barkes likewise, the one called The
        <ship>Gabriel</ship>, whereof <person>Master Fenton</person>, a Gentleman of <person>my Lord of Warwikes</person>, was
        Captaine: accompanied with seuen score Gentlemen, souldiers, and sailers,
        well furnished with victuals, and other prouision necessarie for one halfe
        yeere, on this his second voyage, for the further discouering of the
        passage to <place>Cathay</place>, and other Countreys, thereunto adiacent, by West and
        Northwest nauigations: which passage or way, is supposed to bee on the
        North and Northwest part of <place>America</place>: and the said <place>America</place> to be an Island
        inuironed with the sea, where through our Merchants may haue course and
        recourse with their merchandize, from these our Northernmost parts of
        <place>Europe</place>, to those Orientall coasts of <place>Asia</place>, in much shorter time, and with
        greater benefite then any others, to their no little commoditie and profite
        that do or shall frequent the same. <person>Our said Captaine and General</person> of this
        present voyage and company hauing the yeere before, with two little
        pinnesses, to his great danger, and no small commendations, giuen a worthy
        attempt towards the performance thereof, is also prest, when occasion shall
        be ministred (to the benefite of his Prince, and natiue Countrey) to
        aduenture himelfe further therein. As for the second voyage, it seemeth
        sufficient that he hath better explored and searched the commodities of
        those people and Countreys, which in his first voyage the yeere before he
        had found out.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The Islands Orcades, or Orkney.</sidenote> Vpon which considerations, the
        day and yeere before expressed, we departed from <place>Blacke Wall</place> to <place>Harwich</place>,
        where making an accomplishment of things necessary, <date date="1577-05-31">the last of May</date> we
        hoised vp sailes, and with a merrie winde the <date date="1577-06-07">7. of Iune</date> we arriued at the
        <place>Islands called Orcades, or vulgarly Orkney</place>, being in number 30. subiect and
        adiacent to <place>Scotland</place> where we made prouision of fresh water; in the doing
        wherof <person>our Generall</person> licensed the Gentlemen and souldiers for their
        recreation to go on shore. <sidenote>The Orcadians upon smal occasion flee
        their home.</sidenote> At our landing, the people fled from their poore cottages,
        with shrikes and alarms, to warne their neighbours of enemies, but by
        gentle perswasions we reclamed them to their houses. It seemeth they are
        often frighted with Pirats, or some other enemies, that mooue them to such
        sudden feare. Their houses are very simply builded with Pibble stone,
        without any chimneis, the fire being made in the middest thereof. The good
        man, wife, children, and other of their family eate and sleepe on the one
        side of the house, and the cattell on the other, very beastly and rudely,
        in respect of ciuilitie. <sidenote>No wood in Orkney.</sidenote> They are destitute
        of wood, their fire is turffes, and Cowshards. They haue corne, bigge, and
        oates, with which they pay their Kings rent, to the maintenance of his
        house. They take great quantitie of fish, which they dry in the wind and
        Sunne. They dresse their meat very filthily, and eate it without salt.
        Their apparell is after the rudest sort of <place>Scotland</place>. Their money is all
        base. Their Church and religion is reformed according to the Scots.
        <sidenote>Fisher men of England haue daily traffique to Orkney.</sidenote> The
        fisher men of <place>England</place> can better declare the dispositions of those people
        then I: wherefore I remit other their vsages to their reports, as yeerely
        repaires thither, in their course to and from Island for fish.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>In Iune and Iuly no night in those West and Northwest regions.</sidenote>
        We departed herehence the <date date="1577-06-08">8. of Iune</date>, and followed our course betweene West
        and Northwest, vntill the <date date="1577-07-04">4. of Iuly</date>: all which time we had no night, but
        that easily, and without any impediment we had when we were so disposed,
        the fruition of our bookes, and other pleasures to passe away the time: a
        thing of no small moment, to such as wander in vnknowen seas, and long
        nauigations, especially, when both the winds and raging surges do passe
        their common and wonted course. This benefite endureth in those parts not
        6. weekes, while the sunne is neere the Tropike of Cancer: but where the
        pole is raised to 70. or 80. degrees, it continueth much longer.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Great abundance of Firre trees floting in the sea.</sidenote> All along
        these seas, after we were <date date="1577-06-14">sixe dayes sailing from Orkney</date>, we met floting in
        the sea, great Firre trees, which as we iudged, were with the furie of
        great floods rooted vp, and so driuen into the sea. Island hath almost no
        other wood nor fuell, but such as they take vp vpon their coastes.
        <sidenote>Inquire further of this current.</sidenote> It seemeth, that these trees
        are driuen from some part of the <place>New found land</place>, with the current that
        setteth from the West to the East.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <date date="1577-07-04">4. of Iuly</date> we came within the making of <place>Frisland</place>. From this shoare
        10. or 12. leagues, we met great Islands of yce, of halfe a mile, some
        more, some lesse in compasse, shewing aboue the sea, 30. or 40. fathoms,
        and as we supposed fast on ground, where with our lead we could scarse
        sound the bottome for depth.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Yce, snow, and haile in Iune and Iuly.</sidenote> Here, in place of
        odoriferous and fragrant smels of sweete gums, and pleasant notes of
        musicall birdes, which other Countreys in more temperate Zones do yeeld,
        wee tasted the most boisterous Boreal blasts mixt with snow and haile, in
        the moneths of Iune and Iuly, nothing inferior to our vntemperate winter: a
        sudden alteration, and especially in a place or Paralelle, where the Pole
        is not eleuate aboue 61. degrees: at which height other Countreys more to
        the North, yea vnto 70. degrees, shew themselues more temperate then this
        doth.
      </para>

      <para>
        All along this coast yce lieth, as a continuall bulwarke, and so defendeth
        the countrey, that those that would land there, incur great danger. <person>Our
        Generall</person> 3. dayes together attempted with the ship boate to haue gone on
        shoare, which for that without great danger he could not accomplish, he
        deferred it vntill a more conuenient time. All along the coast lie very
        high mountains covered with snow, except in such places, where through the
        steepenes of the mountaines of force it must needs fall. Foure dayes
        coasting along this land, we found no signe of habitation.
        <sidenote>Friseland subiect to fogge.</sidenote> Little birds, whiche we iudged to haue lost
        the shore, by reason of thicke fogges which that Countrey is much subiect
        vnto, came flying into our ships, which causeth vs to suppose, that the
        Countrey is both more tollerable, and also habitable within, then the
        outward shore maketh shew or signification.
      </para>

      <para>
        From hence we departed <date date="1577-07-08">the eight of Iuly</date>: and the <date date="1577-07-16">16. of the same</date>, we came
        with the making of land, which land <person>our Generall</person> the yeere before had named
        The <place>Queenes foreland</place>, being an Island as we iudge, lying neere the supposed
        continent with <place>America</place>: and on the other side, opposite to the same, one
        other Island called <place>Halles Isle</place>, after the name of <person>the Master of the ship</person>,
        neere adiacent to the firme land, supposed continent with <place>Asia</place>.
        <sidenote>Frobishers streight.</sidenote> Betweene the which two Islands there is a large
        entrance or streight, called <place>Frobishers streight</place>, after the name of <person>our
        Generall</person>, the firste finder thereof. This said streight is supposed to haue
        passage into the <place>sea of Sur</place>, which I leaue vnknowen as yet.
      </para>

      <para>
        It seemeth that either here, or not farre hence, the sea should haue more
        large entrance, then in other parts within the frozen or vntemperate Zone:
        and that some contrary tide, either from the East or West, with maine force
        casteth out that great quantity of yce, which commeth floting from this
        coast, euen vnto <place>Friseland</place>, causing that Countrey to seeme more vntemperate
        then others, much more Northerly then the same.
      </para>

      <para>
        I cannot iudge that any temperature vnder the Pole, the time of the Sunnes
        Northerne declination being halfe a yere together, and one whole day,
        (considering that the Sunnes eleuation surmounteth not 23. degrees and 30.
        minuts) can haue power to <sidenote>Islands of yce comparable to
        mountaines.</sidenote> dissolue such monstrous and huge yce, comparable to great
        mountaines, except by some other force, as by swift currents and tides,
        with the hope of the said day of halfe a yeere.
      </para>

      <para>
        Before we came within the making of these lands we tasted cold stormes, in
        so much that it seemed we had changed summer with winter, if the length of
        the dayes had not remooued vs from that opinion.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Captaine Frobisher his speciall care and diligence for the
        benefite of his Prince and Countrey.</sidenote> At our first comming, the straights
        seemed to be shut vp with a long mure of yce, which gaue no litle cause of
        discomfort vnto vs all: but <person>our Generall</person>, (to whose diligence imminent
        dangers, and difficult attempts seemed nothing, in respect of his willing
        mind, for the commoditie of <person>his Prince</person> and Countrey,) with two little
        Pinnesses prepared of purpose, passed twise thorow them to the East shore,
        and the Ilands thereunto adiacent: and the ship, with the two Barks lay off
        and on something further into the sea, from the danger of the yce.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The order of the people appearing on shoare.</sidenote> Whilest he was
        searching the Countrey neere the shoare, some of the people of the Countrey
        shewed themselues leaping and dauncing, with strange shrikes and cries,
        which gaue no little admiration to our men. <person>Our Generall</person> desirous to allure
        them vnto him by faire meanes, caused kniues, and other things to be
        profered vnto them, which they would not take at our hands: but being laid
        on the ground, and the party going away, they came and tooke vp, leauing
        some thing of theirs to counteruaile the same. <sidenote>Fierce and bold
        people.</sidenote> At the length two of them leauing their weapons, came downe to <person>our
        Generall and Master</person>, who did the like to them, commanding the company to
        stay, and went vnto them: who after certaine dumbe signes, and mute
        congratulations, began to lay handes vpon them, but they deliuerly escaped,
        and ranne to their bowes and arrowes, and came fiercely vpon them, (not
        respecting the rest of our companie which were readie for their defence,)
        but with their arrowes hurt diuers of them: <sidenote>One taken.</sidenote> we tooke
        the one, and the other escaped.
      </para>

      <para>
        Whilest <person>our Generall</person> was busied in searching the Countrey, and <place>those
        Islands</place> adiacent on the Eastshoare, the ship and barkes hauing great care,
        not to put farre into the sea from him, for that he had small store of
        victuals, were forced to abide in a cruell tempest, chancing in the night,
        amongst and in the thickest of the yce, which was so monstrous, that euen
        the least of a thousand had bene of force sufficient, to haue shiuered our
        ship and barks into small portions, if God (who in all necessities, hath
        care vpon the infirmitie of man) had not prouided for this our extremitie a
        sufficient remedie through the light of the night, whereby we might well
        discerne to flee from such imminent dangers, which we auoyded with 14.
        Bourdes in one watch the space of 4 houres. <sidenote>Richard Cox, Master
        gunner. Master Iackman. Andrew Dier.</sidenote> If we had not incurred this danger
        amongst those monstrous Islands of yce, we should haue lost our Generall
        and Master, and the most of our best sailers, which were on shoare
        destitute of victuals: but by the valure of our Master Gunner, <person>Master
        Iackman</person>, and <person>Andrew Dier</person>, the Masters Mates, men expert both in nauigation,
        and other good qualities, wee were all content to incurre the dangers afore
        rehearsed, before we would with our owne safetie, runne into the seas, to
        the destruction of <person>our sayd Generall</person>, and his company.
      </para>

      <para>
        The day following, being the <date date="1577-07-19">19. of Iulie</date>, <person>our captaine</person> returned to the
        ship, with report of supposed riches, which shewed it selfe in the bowels
        of those barren mountaines, wherewith wee were all satisfied.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Iackmans sound.</sidenote> Within foure daies after we had bene at the
        entrance of the streights, the Northwest and West winds dispersed the yce
        into the sea, and made vs a large <place>entrance into the streights</place>, so that
        without any impediment, on <date date="1577-07-19">the 19. of Iulie</date> we entred them, and <date date="1577-07-20">the 20.
        thereof</date>, <person>our Generall and Master</person> with great diligence, sought out and
        sounded the West shoare, and found out a faire Harborough for the ship and
        barkes to ride in, and named it after our Masters mate, <place>Iackmans sound</place>, and
        brought the ship, barkes and all their company to safe anker, except one
        man, which died by Gods visitation.
      </para>

      <para>
        At our first arriuall, after the ship rode at anker, our generall, with
        such company as could well be spared from the ships, in marching order
        entred the lande, hauing speciall care by exhortations, that at our
        entrance thereinto, wee should all with one voyce, kneeling vpon our knees,
        chiefly thanke God for our safe arriuall: secondly beseech him, that it
        would please his diuine Maiestie, long to continue <person>our Queene</person>, for whom he,
        and all the rest of our company in this order tooke possession of the
        <sidenote>Possession taken.</sidenote> Countrey: and thirdly, that by our Christian
        studie and endeuour, those barbarous people trained vp in Paganisme, and
        infidelitie, might be reduced to the knowledge of true religion, and to the
        hope of saluation in Christ our Redeemer. With other words very apt to
        signifie his willing mind, and affection toward his Prince and Countrey:
        whereby all suspicion of an vndutifull subiect, may credibly be iudged to
        be vtterly exempted from his mind. All the rest of the Gentlemen and other
        deserue worthily herein their due praise and commendation.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        These things in this order accomplished, <person>our Generall</person> commanded all the
        company to be obedient in things needfull for our owne safegard, to <person>Master
        Fenton</person>, <person>Master Yorke</person>, and <person>Master Beast</person> his Lieutenant, while he was
        occupied in other necessarie affaires, concerning our comming thither.
      </para>

      <para>
        After this order we marched through the Countrey, with Ensigne displaied,
        so farre as was thought needfull, and now and then heaped vp stones on high
        mountaines, and other places in token of possession, as likewise to
        signifie vnto such as hereafter may chance to arriue there, that possession
        is taken in the behalfe of some other Prince, by those who first found out
        the Countrey.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Yce needfull to be regarded of sea faring men.</sidenote> Who so maketh
        nauigations to those Countreys, hath not onely extreme winds, and furious
        sea to encounter withall, but also many monstrous and great Islands of yce;
        a thing both rare, wonderfull, and greatly to be regarded.
      </para>

      <para>
        We were forced sundry times, while the ship did ride here at anker, to haue
        continuall watch, with boats and men ready with halsers to knit fast vnto
        such yce, as with the ebbe and flood were tossed to and fro in the
        harborough, and with force of oares to hale them away, for endangering the
        ship.
      </para>

      <para>
        <person>Our Generall</person> certaine dayes searched this supposed continent with <place>America</place>,
        and not finding the commodity to answere his expectation, after he had made
        triall thereof he departed thence with two little barks, and men sufficient
        to the East shore being <place>the supposed continent of Asia</place>, and left the ship
        with most of the Gentlemen, souldier, and sailers, vntill such time as he
        either thought good to send or come for them.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Stones glister with sparkles like gold.</sidenote> The stones of this
        supposed continent with America be altogether sparkled, and glister in the
        Sunne like gold: <sidenote>A common prouerb.</sidenote> so likewise doth the sand in
        the bright water, yet they verifie the old Prouerb: All is not gold that
        glistereth.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The sea Vnicorne.</sidenote> On this West shore we found a dead fish
        floating, which had in his nose a horne streight and torquet, of length
        two yards lacking two ynches, being broken in the top, where we might
        perceiue it hollow, into the which some of our sailers putting spiders they
        presently died. I saw not the triall hereof, but it was reported vnto me of
        a trueth: by the verture whereof we supposed it to be the sea Vnicorne.
      </para>

      <para>
        After <person>our Generall</person> had found out good harborough for the ship and barks to
        anker in, and also such store of supposed gold ore as he thought himselfe
        satisfied withall, he returned to the <ship>Michael</ship>, whereof <person>Master Yorke</person>
        aforesaid was Captaine, accompanied with our master and his Mate: who
        coasting along the West shore not farre from whence the ship rode, they
        perceived a faire harborough, and willing to sound the same, at the
        entrance thereof they espied two tents of Seale skins, vnto which the
        Captaine, our said Master, and other company resorted. <sidenote>The
        people fled at the sight of our men.</sidenote> At the sight of our men the people
        fled into the mountaines: neuerthelesse they went to their tents, where
        leauing certaine trifles of ours, as glasses, bels, kniues, and such like
        things they departed, not taking any thing of theirs, except one dogge.
        They did in like maner leaue behind them a letter, pen, yncke, and paper,
        whereby our men whom the Captaine lost the yere before, and in that peoples
        custody, might (if any of them were aliue) be advertised of our presence
        and being there.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Master Philpot. Master Beast.</sidenote> On the same day after
        consultation had, all the Gentlemen, and others likewise that could be
        spared from the ship, vnder the conduct and leading of <person>Master Philpot</person>,
        (vnto whom in our Generall his absence, and his Lieutenant <person>Master Beast</person>, al
        the rest were obedient) went a shore, determining to see, if by faire means
        we could either allure them to familiarity, or otherwise take some of them,
        and so attaine to some knowledge of those men whom <person>our Generall</person> lost the
        yeere before.
      </para>

      <para>
        At our comming backe againe to the place where their tents were before,
        they had remooued their tents further into the said Bay or Sound, where
        they might if they were driuen from the land, flee with their boates into
        the sea. We parting our selues into two companies, and compassing a
        mountaine came suddenly vpon them by land, who espying vs, without any
        tarrying fled to their boates, leauing the most part of their oares behind
        them for haste, and rowed downe the bay, where our two Pinesses met them
        and droue them to shore: but if they had had all their oares, so swift are
        they in rowing, it had bene lost time to haue chased them.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <sidenote>A fierce assault of a few.</sidenote> When they were landed they fiercely
        assaulted our men with their bowes and arrowes, who wounded three of them
        with our arrowes; and perceiuing themselues thus hurt, they desperatly
        leapt off the Rocks into the Sea, and drowned themselues: which if they had
        not done, but had submitted themselues, or if by any meanes we could haue
        taken them aliue (being their enemies as they iudged) we would both haue
        saued them, and also haue sought remedy to cure their wounds receiued at
        our hands. But they altogether voyd of humanity, and ignorant what mercy
        meaneth, in extremities looke for no other then death: and perceiuing they
        should fall into our hands, thus miserably by drowning rather desired death
        then otherwise to be saued by vs: the rest perceiuing their fellowes in
        this distresse, fled into the high mountaines. Two women not being so apt
        to escape as the men were, the one for her age, and the other being
        incombred with a yong child, we tooke. The old wretch, whom diuers of our
        Saylers supposed to be eyther a deuill, or a witch, had her buskins plucked
        off, to see if she were clouen footed, and for her ougly hew and deformity
        we let her go: the yong woman and the child we brought away. We named the
        place where they were slaine, Bloodie point: and the Bay or Harborough,
        Yorks sound, after the name of one of the Captaines of the two Barks.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Faire meanes not able to allure them to familiarity.</sidenote> Having
        this knowledge both of their fiercenesse and cruelty, and perceiuing that
        faire meanes as yet is not able to allure them to familiarity, we disposed
        our selues, contrary to our inclination, something to be cruel, returned to
        their tents and made a spoyle of the same: where we found an old shirt, a
        doublet, a girdle, and also shoes of our men, whom we lost the yeere
        before: on nothing else vnto them belonging could we set our eyes.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Boates of skinnes.</sidenote> Their riches are not gold, siluer or
        precious Drapery, but their tents and boates, made of the skins of red
        Deare and Seale skins; also dogges like vnto woolues, but for the most part
        black, with other trifles, more to be wondred at for their strangenesse,
        then for any other commoditie needefull for our vse.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Our departure from the West shoare.</sidenote> Thus returning to our ship
        <date date="1577-08-03">the 3. August</date>, we departed from <place>the West shore supposed firme with America</place>,
        after we had ankered there 13. dayes: and so <date date="1577-08-04">the 4. thereof</date> we came to <person>our
        Generall</person> on the East shore and ankered in a faire Harborough name <place>Anne
        Warwickes sound</place>, vnto which is annexed <place>an Island both named after the
        Countesse of Warwicke, Anne Warwickes sound and Isle</place>.
      </para>

      <para>
        In this Isle <person>our Generall</person> thought good for this voyage, to fraight both the
        ship and barkes, with such stone or supposed gold minerall, as he iudged to
        counteruaile the charges of his first, and this his second nauigation to
        these Countreys.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The countrey people shew themselues vnto vs.</sidenote> In the meane time
        of our abode here some of the countrey people came to shew themselues vnto
        vs, sundry times on the maine shore, neere adiacent to the saide Isle. Our
        Generall desirous to haue some newes of his men, whom he lost the yeere
        before, with some company with him repaired with the ship boat to common,
        or signe with them for familiaritie, whereunto he is perswaded to bring
        them. They at the first shew made tokens, that three of his fiue men were
        aliue, and desired penne, ynck, and paper, and that within three or foure
        dayes they would returne, and (as we iudged) bring those of our men which
        were liuing, with them.
      </para>

      <para>
        They also made signes or tokens of <person>their king, whom they called Cacough</person>,
        and how he was carried on mens shoulders, and a man farre surmounting any
        of our company, in bignesse and stature.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Their vsage in traffique or exchange.</sidenote> With these tokens and
        signes of writing, penne, yncke, and paper was deliuered them, which they
        would not take at our hands, but being laid vpon the shore, and the partie
        gone away, they tooke vp: which likewise they do when they desire any thing
        for change of theirs, laying for that which is left so much as they thinke
        will counteruaile the same, and not coming neere together. It seemeth they
        haue been vsed to this trade or traffique, with some other people
        adioining, or not farre distant from their Countrey.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The people shew themselues the third time.</sidenote> After 4. dayes some
        of them shewed themselues vpon the firme land, but not where they were
        before. <person>Our General</person> very glad thereof, supposing to heare of our men, went
        from the Island, with the boat, and sufficient company with him. They
        seemed very glad, and allured him about a certaine point of the land:
        behind which they might perceiue a company of the crafty villaines to lye
        lurking, whom our Generall would not deale withall, for that he knew not
        what company they were, and so with few signes dismissed them and returned
        to his company.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The people shew themselues againe on firme land.</sidenote> An other time
        as <person>our said Generall</person> was coasting the Countrey with two little Pinnesses,
        whereby at our returne he might make the better relation thereof, three of
        the crafty villans, with a white skin allured vs to them. <sidenote>Their
        first meanes to allure vs to shore.</sidenote> Once again, <person>our Generall</person>, for that he
        hoped to heare of his men, went towards them: at our comming neere the
        shore whereon they were, we might perceiue a number of them lie hidden
        behind great stones, and those 3. in sight labouring by all meanes possible
        that some would come on land: and perceiuing we made no hast by words nor
        friendly signes, which they vsed by clapping of their hands, and being
        without weapon, and but 3. in sight, they sought further meanes to prouoke
        vs therevnto. <sidenote>Their second meanes.</sidenote> One alone laid flesh on the
        shore, which we tooke vp with the Boate hooke, as necessary victuals for
        the relieuing of the man, woman, and child, whom we had taken: for that as
        yet they could not digest our meat: whereby they perceiued themselues
        deceiued of their expectation, for all their crafty allurements.
        <sidenote>Their third and craftiest allurement.</sidenote> Yet once againe to make (as it were)
        a full shew of their craftie natures, and subtile sleights, to the intent
        thereby to haue intrapped and taken some of our men, one of them
        counterfeited himselfe impotent and lame of his legs, who seemed to descend
        to the water side, with great difficulty: and to couer his craft the more,
        one of his fellowes came downe with him, and in such places where he seemed
        vnable to passe, he tooke him on his shoulders, set him by the water side,
        and departed from him, leauing him (as it should seeme) all alone, who
        playing his counterfeit pageant very well, thought thereby to prouoke some
        of vs to come on shore, not fearing, but that one of vs might make our
        party good with a lame man.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Compassion to cure a crafty lame man.</sidenote> <person>Our Generall</person> hauing
        compassion of his impotency, thought good (if it were possible) to cure him
        thereof: wherefore he caused a souldier to shoote at him with his Caleeuer,
        which grased before his face. The counterfeit villeine deliuerly fled,
        without any impediment at all, and got him to his bow and arrowes, and the
        rest from their lurking holes, with their weapons, bowes, arrowes, slings,
        and darts. <person>Our Generall</person> caused some caleeuers to be shot off at them,
        whereby some being hurt, they might hereafter stand in more feare of vs.
      </para>

      <para>
        This was all the answere for this time we could haue of our men, or of <person>our
        Generals</person> letter. Their crafty dealing at these three seuerall times being
        thus manifest vnto vs, may plainely shew their disposition in other things
        to be correspondent. We iudged that they vsed these stratagemes, thereby to
        haue caught some of vs, for the deliuering of the man, woman and child whom
        we had taken.
      </para>

      <para>
        They are men of a large corporature, and good proportion: their colour is
        not much vnlike the Sunne burnt Countrey man, who laboureth daily in the
        Sunne for his liuing.
      </para>

      <para>
        They weare their haire something long, and cut before either with stone or
        knife, very disorderly. Their women weare their haire long and knit vp with
        two loupes, shewing forth on either side of their faces, and the rest
        foltred vpon a knot. Also some of their women race their faces
        proportionally, as chinne, cheekes, and forehead, and the wrists of their
        hands, wherevpon they lay a colour which continueth darke azurine.
      </para>

      <para>
        They eate their meat all raw, both flesh, fish, and foule, or something per
        boyled with blood and a little water which they drinke. For lacke of water
        they will eate yce, that is hard frosen, as pleasantly as we will do Sugar
        Candie, or other Sugar.
      </para>

      <para>
        If they for necessities sake stand in need of the premisses, such grasse as
        the countrey yeeldeth they plucke vp and eate, not deintily, or salletwise
        to allure their stomacks to appetite: but for necessities sake without
        either salt, oiles or washing, like brute beasts deuouring the same. They
        neither vse table, stoole, or table cloth for comlines; but when they are
        imbrued with blood knuckle deepe, and their kniues in like sort, they vse
        their tongues as apt instruments to lick them cleane: in doing whereof they
        are assured to loose none of their victuals.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Dogges like vnto wolues.</sidenote> They frank or keepe certaine dogs not
        much vnlike Wolues, which they yoke togither, as we do oxen and horses, to
        a sled or traile: and so carry their necessaries ouer the yce and snow from
        place to place: as the captiue, whom we haue, made perfect signes.
        <sidenote>They eate dogs flesh.</sidenote> And when these dogs are not apt for the
        same vse: or when with hunger they are constrained for lacke of other
        victuals, they eate them: so that they are as needfull for them in respect
        of their bignesse, as our oxen are for vs.
      </para>

      <para>
        They apparell themselues in the skins of such beasts as they kill, sewed
        together with the sinewes of them. All the foule which they kill, they
        skin, and make thereof one kind of garment or other to defend them from the
        cold.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Hoods and tailes to their apparell.</sidenote> They make their apparel
        with hoods and tailes, which tailes they giue when they thinke to gratifie
        any friendship shewed vnto them: a great signe of friendship with them. The
        men haue them not so side as the women.
      </para>

      <para>
        The men and women weare their hose close to their legges, from the wast to
        the knee without any open before, as well the one kind as the other. Vpon
        their legges they weare hose of leather, with the furre side inward two or
        three paire on at once, and especially the women. In those hose they put
        their kniues, needles, and other thing needfull to beare about. They put a
        bone within their hose, which reacheth from the foote to the knee,
        whereupon they draw the said hose, and so in place of garters they are
        holden from falling downe about their feete.
      </para>

      <para>
        They dresse their skinnes very soft and souple with the haire on. In cold
        weather or Winter they weare the furre side inward: and Summer outward.
        Other apparell they haue none but the said skinnes.
      </para>

      <para>
        Those beasts, fishes, and foules, which they kill, are their meat, drinke,
        apparell, houses, bedding, hose, shooes, threed, and sailes for their
        boates, with many other necessaries whereof they stand in need, and almost
        all their riches.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Their houses of Seale skins and firre.</sidenote> Their houses are tents
        made of Seale skins, pitched vp with 4. Firre quarters foure square meeting
        at the top, and the skins sewed together with sinews, and laid thereupon:
        they are so pitched vp, that the entrance into them is alwayes South or
        against the Sunne.
      </para>

      <para>
        They haue other sorts of houses which we found not to be inhabited, which
        are raised with stones and Whale bones, and a skinne layd ouer them, to
        with stand the raine, or other weather: the entrance of them being not much
        vnlike an Ouens mouth, whereto I thinke they resort for a time to fish,
        hunt, and foule, and so leaue them vntil the next time they come thither
        again.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Their weapons of defence.</sidenote> Their weapons are bowes, arrowes,
        darts, and slings. Their bowes are of wood of a yard long, sinewed at the
        back with strong sinews, not glued too, but fast girded and tyed on. Their
        bow strings are likewise sinewes. Their arrowes are three pieces nocked
        with bone, and ended with bone, with those two ends, and the wood in the
        midst, they passe not in length halfe a yard or little more. They are
        fethered with two fethers the penne end being cut away, and the fethers
        layd vpon the arrow with the broad side to the wood; insomuch that they
        seeme when they are tyed on, to haue foure fethers. <sidenote>Three sorts
        of heads to their arrowes.</sidenote> They haue also three sorts of heads to those
        arrowes: one sort of stone or yron, proportioned like to a heart: the
        second sort of bone, much like vnto a stopt head, with a hooke on the same:
        the third sort of bone likewise made sharpe at both sides, and sharpe
        pointed. They are not made very fast but lightly tyed to, or else set in a
        nocke, that vpon small occasion the arrowes leaue these heads behind them:
        and they are of small force, except they be very neere when they shoote.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>two sorts of darts.</sidenote> Their Darts are made of two sorts: the one
        with many forkes of bones in the fore end and likewise in the midst: their
        proportions are not much vnlike our toasting yrons, but longer: these they
        cast out of an instrument of wood, very readily. The other sort is greater
        then the first aforesayd, with a long bone made sharpe on both sides not
        much vnlike a Rapier, which I take to bee their most hurtfull weapon.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Two sortes of boates made of leather.</sidenote> They haue two sorts of
        boats made of leather, set out on the inner side with quarters of wood,
        artificially tyed with thongs of the same: the greater sort are not much
        vnlike our wherries, wherein sixteene or twenty men may sit: they haue for
        a sayle drest the guts of such beasts as they kill very fine and thinne,
        which they sew together: the other boate is but for one man to sit and row
        in with one oare. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <sidenote>They vse to foule, fish, and hunt.</sidenote> Their order of fishing,
        hunting, and fouling are with these said weapons; but in what sort, or how
        they vse them we haue no perfect knowledge as yet.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>It is to be supposed that their inhabiting is elsewhere.</sidenote> I can
        suppose their abode or habitation not to be here, for that neither their
        houses or apparell, are of such force to withstand the extremity of cold,
        that the Countrey seemeth to be infected with all: neither do I see any
        signe likely to performe the same.
      </para>

      <para>
        Those houses or rather dennes which stand there, haue no signe of footway,
        or any thing else troden, which is one of the chiefest tokens of
        habitation. And those tents which they bring with them, when they haue
        sufficiently hunted and fished, they remoue to other places: and when they
        haue sufficiently stored them of such victuals, as the Countrey yeeldeth or
        bringeth forth, they returne to their winter stations or habitations. This
        coniecture do I make, for the infertility which I coniecture to be in that
        Countrey.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Their vse of yron.</sidenote> They haue some yron whereof they make arrow
        heads, kniues, and other little instruments, to worke their boates, bowes,
        arrowes, and darts withall, which are very vnapt to doe any thing withall
        but with great labour.
      </para>

      <para>
        It seemeth that they haue conuersation with some other people, of whom for
        exchange they should receiue the same. They are greatly delighted with any
        thing that is bright, or giueth a sound.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Anthropophagi.</sidenote> What knowledge they haue of God, or what Idoll
        they adore, we haue no perfect intelligence, I thinke them rather
        Anthropophagi, or deuourers of mans flesh then otherwise: for that there is
        no flesh or fish which they find dead (smell it neuer so filthily) but they
        will eate it, as they finde it without any other dressing. A loathsome
        thing, either to the beholders or hearers.
      </para>

      <para>
        There is no maner of creeping beast hurtfull, except some Spiders (which as
        many affirme, are signes of great store of gold) and also certaine stinging
        Gnattes, which bite so fiercely, that the place where they bite shortly
        after swelleth, and itcheth very sore.
      </para>

      <para>
        They make signes of certaine people that weare bright plates of gold in
        their foreheads, and other places of their bodies.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Description of the Countreis.</sidenote> <place>The Countreys on both sides the
        streights</place> lye very high with rough stony mountaines, and great quantitie of
        snow thereon. There is very little plaine ground and no grasse, except a
        little which is much like vnto mosse that groweth on soft ground, such as
        we get Turffes in. There is no wood at all. To be briefe there is nothing
        fit or profitable for the vse of man, which that Countrey with roote
        yeeldeth or bringeth forth: Howbeit there is great quantity of Deere, whose
        skins are like vnto Asses, there heads or hornes doe farre exceede, as well
        in length as also in breadth, any in these our parts or Countreys: their
        feete likewise are as great as our oxens, which we measured to be seuen or
        eight ynches in breadth. There are also hares, wolues, fishing beares, and
        sea foule of sundry sorts.
      </para>

      <para>
        As the Countrey is barren and vnfertile, so are they rude and of no
        capacitie to culture the same to any perfection; but are contented by their
        hunting, fishing, and fouling, with raw flesh and warme blood to satisfie
        their greedy panches, which is their only glory.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>A signe of Earthquakes or thunder.</sidenote> There is great likelihood of
        Earthquakes or thunder: for that there are huge and monstrous mountaines,
        whose greatest substance are stones, and those stones so shaken with some
        extraordinarie meanes that one is separated from another, which is
        discordant from all other Quarries.
      </para>
        
      <para>
        <sidenote>No riuers, but such as the Sunne doth cause to come of Snow.</sidenote>
        There are no riuers or running springs, but such as through the heate of
        the Sunne, with such water as decendeth from the mountaines and hilles,
        whereon great drifts of snow do lie, are engendred.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>A probability that there should be neither spring or riuer in
        the ground.</sidenote> It argueth also that there should be none: for that the earth,
        which with the extremitie of the Winter is so frosen within, that that
        water which should haue recourse within the same to maintaine springs, hath
        not his motion, whereof great waters haue their originall, as by experience
        is seene otherwhere. Such valleis as are capable to receiue the water, that
        in the Summer time by the operation of the Sunne decendeth from great
        abundance of snowe, which continually lyeth on the mountaines and hath no
        passage, sinketh into the earth and so vanisheth away, without any runnell
        aboue the earth, by which occasion or continuall standing of the said
        water, the earth is opened, and the great frost yeeldeth to the force
        thereof, which in other places foure or fiue fathomes within the ground for
        lacke of the said moisture, the earth (euen in the very summer time) is
        frosen, and so combineth the stones together, that scarcely instruments
        with great force can vnknit them.
      </para>

      <para>
        Also where the water in those valleis can haue no such passage away, by the
        continuance of time in such order as is before rehearsed, the yeerely
        descent from the mountaines filleth them full, that at the lowest banke of
        the same, they fall into the valley, and so continue as fishing Ponds or
        Stagnes in Summer time full of water, and in the Winter hard frosen: as by
        skarres that remaine thereof in Summer may easily be perceiued: so that the
        heat of Summer is nothing comparable or of force to dissolue the extremitie
        of cold that commeth in Winter.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Springs nourish gold.</sidenote> Neuerthelesse I am assured that below the
        force of the frost within the earth, the waters haue recourse, and emptie
        themselues out of sight into the Sea, which through the extremitie of the
        frost are constrained to doe the same: by which occasion the earth within
        is kept the warmer, and springs haue their recourse, which is the only
        nutriment of golde and Minerals within the same.
      </para>

      <para>
        There is much to be sayd of the commodities of these Countreys, which are
        couched within the bowels of the earth, which I let passe till more perfect
        triall be made thereof.
      </para>

      <para>
        <date date="1577-08-24">The 24. of August</date> after we had satisfied our minds with fraight sufficient
        for our vessels, though not our couetous desires with such knowledge of the
        Countrey people, and other commodities as are before rehearsed, we departed
        therehence. <sidenote>Our departure from those Countreys.</sidenote> <date date="1577-09-17">The 17. of
        September</date> we fell with <place>the lands end of England</place>, and so sailed to <place>Milford
        Hauen</place>, from whence <person>our Generall</person> rode to the Court for order, to what Port
        or Hauen to conduct the ship.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>How and when we lost our 2. Barks which God neuerthelesse
        restored.</sidenote> We lost our two Barkes in the way homeward, the one <date date="1577-08-29">the 29. of
        August</date>, the other <date date="1577-08-21">the 21. of the same moneth</date>, by occasion of great tempest
        and fogge. Howbeit God restored the one to <place>Bristowe</place>, and the other made his
        course by <place>Scotland</place> to <place>Yermouth</place>. In this voyage we lost two men, one in the
        way by Gods visitation, and the other homeward cast ouer borde with a surge
        of the Sea.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The conclusion.</sidenote> I could declare vnto the Readers, the latitude
        and longitude of such places and regions as we haue bene at, but not
        altogether so perfectly as our masters and others, with many circumstances
        of tempests and other accidents incident to Sea-faring men, which seeme not
        altogether strange, but I let them passe to their reports as men most apt
        to set forth and declare the same. I haue also left the names of the
        Countreys on both the shores vntouched, for lacke of vnderstanding the
        peoples language: as also for sundry respects, not needfull as yet to be
        declared.
      </para>

      <para>
        Countreys new discovered where commoditie is to be looked for, doe better
        accord with a new name giuen by the discouerers, then an vncertaine name by
        a doubtfull Authour.
      </para>

      <para>
        <person>Our generall</person> named sundry Islands, Mountaines, Capes, and Harboroughs after
        the names of diuers Noble men and other gentlemen his friends, as wel on
        the one shore as also on the other.
      </para>
  </extract>

  <extract id="E003">
      <title>
        The third and last voyage vnto <place>Meta Incognita</place>, made by <person>M. Martin Frobisher</person>, in the yeere 1578. Written by <person>Thomas Ellis</person>.
      </title>

      <para>
        These are to let you know, that vpon the <date date="1578-05-25">25. of May</date>, the <ship>Thomas Allen</ship> being
        Viceadmirall whose Captaine was <person>M. Yorke</person>, <person>M. Gibbes</person> Master, <person>Christopher
        Hall</person> Pilot, accompanied with the Reareadmiral named the <ship>Hopewel</ship>, whose
        Captaine was <person>M. Henrie Carewe</person>, the <person>M. Andrewe Dier</person>, and certaine other
        ships came to <place>Grauesend</place>, where wee ankered and abode the comming of our
        Fleete which were not yet come.
      </para>

      <para>
        <date date="1578-05-27">The 27. of the same moneth</date> our Fleete being nowe come together, and all
        things prest in a readinesse, the wind fauouring, and tide seruing, we
        being of sailes in number eight, waied ankers and hoised our sailes toward
        Harwich to meete with our Admirall, and the residue which then and there
        abode arriuall: where we safely arriued <date date="1578-05-28">the 28. thereof</date>, finding there our
        Admirall, whom we with the discharge of certaine pieces saluted, acording
        to order and duety, and were welcommed with the like courtesie: which being
        finished we landed; where our Generall continued mustering his souldiers
        and Miners, and setting things in order appertaining to the voyage vntill
        <date date="1578-05-31">the last of the said moneth of May</date>, which day we hoised our sailes, and
        committing ourselues to the conducting of Almightie God, we set forward
        toward the west Countrey in such luckie wise and good successe, that by <date date="1578-06-05">the
        fift of Iune</date> we passed <place>the Dursies</place>, being the vtmost part of <place>Ireland</place> to the
        Westward.
      </para>

      <para>
        And here it were not much amisse nor farre from our purpose, if I should a
        little discourse and speake of our aduentures and chances by the way, as
        our landing at <place>Plimmouth</place>, as also the meeting certaine poore men, which
        were robbed and spoyled of all that they had by Pirates and Rouers: amongst
        whom was a man of <place>Bristow</place>, on whom our Generall vsed his liberality, and
        sent him away with letters into <place>England</place>.
      </para>

      <para>
        But because such things are impertinent to the matter, I will returne
        (without any more mentioning of the same) to that from the which I haue
        digressed and swarued, I meane our ships now sailing on the surging seas,
        sometime passing at pleasure with a wished Easterne wind, sometimes
        hindered of our course againe by the Westerne blasts, vntill <date date="1578-06-20">the 20. day of
        the foresayd moneth of Iune</date>, on which day in the morning we fell with
        <place>Frizeland</place>, which is a very hie and cragged land and was almost cleane
        couered with snow, so that we might see nought but craggie rockes and the
        topes of high and huge hilles, sometimes (and for the most part) all
        couered with foggie mists. There might we also perceiue the great Isles of
        yce lying on the seas, like mountaines, some small, some big, of sundry
        kinds of shapes, and such a number of them, that wee could not come neere
        the shore for them.
      </para>

      <para>
        Thus sailing alongst the coast, at the last we saw a place somewhat voyd of
        yce, where our Generall (accompanied with certaine other) went a shore,
        where they sawe certaine tents made of beasts skinnes; and boates much the
        like vnto theirs of <place>Meta Incognita</place>. The tents were furnished with flesh,
        fish, skins, and other trifles: amonst the which was found a boxe of
        nailes: whereby we did coniecture, that they had either Artificers amongst
        them, or els a traffike with some other nation. The men ran away, so that
        wee coulde haue no conference or communication with them. <sidenote>The
        curtesie of our Generall.</sidenote> Our Generall (because hee would haue them no
        more to flee, but rather incouraged to stay through his courteous dealing)
        gaue commaundement that his men should take nothing away with them, sauing
        onely a couple of white dogs, for the which he left pinnes, poynts, kniues,
        and other trifling things, and departed without taking or hurting any
        thing, and so came abord, and hoysed sailes, and passed forwards.
      </para>

      <para>
        But being scarce out of the sight thereof, there fell such a foggy and
        hidious mist that we could not see one another: whereupon we stroke our
        drums, and sounded our trumpets, to the ende we might keepe together: and
        so continued all that day and night till the next day that the mist brake
        vp: so that we might easily perceiue all the ships thus sailing together
        all that day, vntil the next day, being the <date date="1578-06-22">22. of the same</date>: on which day
        wee sawe an infinite number of yce, from the which we cast about to shun
        the danger thereof.
      </para>

      <para>
        But one of our small Barkes named the <ship>Michael</ship>, whose Captaine was <person>Master
        Kinderslie</person>, the master <person>Bartholomew Bull</person>, lost our company, insomuch that we
        could not obteine the sight of her many dayes after, of whom I meane to
        speak further anon when occassion shall be ministred, and opportunitie
        serue. Thus we continued in our course vntill <date date="1578-07-02">the second of Iuly</date>, on which
        day we fell with the <place>Queenes foreland</place>, where we saw so much yce, that we
        thought it vnpossible to get into <place>the Straights</place>; yet at the last we gaue
        the aduenture and entred the yce.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The Michael. The Iudith. M. Fenton. Charles Iackman.</sidenote> Being
        amongst it wee sawe the <ship>Michael</ship>, of whom I spake before, accompanied with
        the <ship>Iudith</ship>, whose Captaine was <person>Master Fenton</person>, the Master <person>Charles Iackman</person>,
        bearing into the foresayd yce, farre distant from vs, who in a storme that
        fell that present night, (whereof I will at large God willing, discourse
        hereafter) were seuered from vs, and being in, wandred vp and downe <place>the
        Straights</place> amongst the yce many dayes in great perill, till at the last, by
        the prouidence of God, they came safely to harbor in their wished Port in
        the <place>Countesse of Warwicks sound</place>, the <date date="1578-07-20">20. of Iuly</date> aforesayd, tenne dayes
        before any of the other shippes: <sidenote>The Countesse of Warwicks
          sound.</sidenote> who going on shore found where the people of the Countrey had bene,
        and had hid their provision in great heapes of stones being both of flesh
        and fish, which they had killed; whereof wee also found great store in
        other places after our arriual. They found also diuers engins, as bowes,
        slings, and darts. They found likewise certaine pieces of the Pinnesse
        which <person>our Generall</person> left there the yeere before, which Pinnesse he had
        sunke, minding to haue it againe the next yeere.
      </para>

      <para>
        Now seeing I haue entreated so much of the Iudith and the Michael: I will
        returne to the rest of the other ships, and will speake a little of the
        storme which fell, with the mishaps that we had, the night that we put into
        the yce: whereof I made mention before.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Our entrance and passage &amp;c.</sidenote> At the first entring into the yce
        in <place>the mouth of the Straights</place>, our passage was very narrow, and difficult
        but being once gotten in, we had a faire open place without any yce for the
        most part, being a league in compasse, the yce being round about vs and
        inclosing vs, as it were, within the pales of a parke. In which place,
        (because it was almost night) we minded to take in our sailes, and lie a
        hull all that night. But the storme so increased, and the waues began to
        mount aloft, which brought the yce so neere vs, and comming on so fast vpon
        vs, that we were faine to beare in and out, where we might espie an open
        place. Thus the yce comming on vs so fast, we were in great danger, looking
        euery houre for death. And thus passed we on in that great danger, seeing
        both our selues and the rest of our ships so troubled and tossed amongst
        the yce, that it would make the strongest heart to relent.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Barke Dionyse.</sidenote> At the last the Barke <ship>Dionyse</ship> being but a weake
        ship, and bruised afore amongst the yce, being so leake that no longer she
        could tarry aboue the water, sanke without sauing any of the goods which
        were within her: which sight so abashed the whole Fleete, that we thought
        verily we should haue tasted of the same sauce. But neuerthelesse we seeing
        them in such danger, manned our boates and saued all men in such wise, that
        not one perished: God be thanked.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Narow shifts for safetie.</sidenote> The storme still increased and the
        yce inclosed vs, so that we were faine to take downe top and top mastes:
        for the yce had so inuironed vs, that we could see neither land nor sea, as
        farre as we could kenne: so that we were faine to cut our cables to hang
        ouer boord for fenders, somewhat to ease the ships sides from the great and
        driry strokes of the yce: some with Capstan barres, some fending off with
        oares, some with plancks of two ynches thicke, which were broken immediatly
        with the force of the yce, some going out vpon the yce to beare it off with
        their shoulders from the ship. But the rigorousnes of the tempest was such,
        and the force of the yce so great, that not onely they burst and spoyled
        the foresaid prouision, but likewise so raised the sides of the ships, that
        it was pitifull to behold, and caused the hearts of many to faint.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Gods prouidence.</sidenote> Thus we continued all that dismall and
        lamentable night plunged in this perplexity, looking for instant death: but
        our God (who neuer leaueth them destitute which call vpon him, although he
        often punisheth for amendements sake) in the morning caused the winds to
        cease, and the fogge which all that night lay on the face of the water to
        cleare: so that we might perceiue about a mile from vs, a certaine place
        cleare from any yce, to the which with an easie breath of wind which our
        God sent vs, we bent our selues. And furthermore, hee prouided better for
        vs then we deserued or hoped for: for when we were in the foresaid cleare
        place, he sent vs a fresh gale at West or at West Southwest, which set vs
        cleare without all the yce. And further he added more: for he sent vs so
        pleasant a day as the like we had not of a long time before, as after
        punishment consolation.
      </para>

      <para>
        Thus we ioyfull wights being at libertie, tooke in all our sailes and lay a
        hull, praysing God for our deliuerance, and stayed to gather together our
        Fleete: which once being done, we seeing that none of them had any great
        hurt, neither any of them wanted, sauing onely they of whom I spake before
        and the ship which was lost, then at the last we hoised our sailes, and lay
        bulting off and on, till such time as it would please God to take away the
        yce that wee might get into <place>the Straights</place>.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>A mountaine of yce appearing in sundry figures.</sidenote> And as we thus
        lay off and on we came by a marueilous huge mountaine of yce, which
        surpassed all the rest that euer we saw: for we iudged it to be neere
        fourescore fathomes aboue water, and we thought it to be a ground for any
        thing that we could perceiue, being there nine score fathoms deepe, and of
        compasse about halfe a mile.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>A fog of long continuance.</sidenote> Also the <date date="1578-07-05">fift of Iuly</date> there fell a
        hidious fogge and mist, that continued till the <date date="1578-07-19">nineteenth of the same</date>: so
        that one shippe could not see another. <sidenote>A current to the
        Northwest.</sidenote> Therefore we were faine to beare a small sayle and to obserue
        the time: but there ran such a current of a tide, that it set vs to the
        Northwest of the <place>Queenes foreland</place> the backside of all <place>the Straights</place>: where
        (through the contagious fogge hauing no sight either of Sunne or Starre) we
        scarce knew where we were. In this fogge <date date="1578-07-10">the tenth of Iuly</date> we lost the
        company of the <ship>Viceadmirall</ship>, the <ship>Anne Francis</ship>, the <ship>Busse of Bridgewater</ship>,
        and the <ship>Francis of Foy</ship>.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The Gabriel. The people offer to traffike with vs.</sidenote> The <date date="1578-07-16">16. day</date>
        one of our small Barkes named The <ship>Gabriel</ship> was sent by <ship>our Generall</ship> to beare
        in with the land to descrie it, where being on land, they met with the
        people of the Countrey, which seemed very humane and ciuill, and offered to
        traffike with our men, profering them foules and skins for kniues, and
        other trifles: whose courtesie caused vs to thinke, that they had small
        conuersation with other of <place>the Straights</place>.
      </para>

      <para>
        Then we bare backe againe to goe with the <place>Queenes foreland</place>: and <date date="1578-07-18">the
        eighteenth day</date> wee came by <place>two Islands</place> whereon we went on shore, and found
        where the people had bene: but we saw none of them. This day we were againe
        in the yce, and like to be in as great perill as we were at the first. For
        through the darknesse and obscuritie of the fogie mist, we were almost run
        on rocks and Islands before we saw them: But God (euen miraculously)
        prouided for vs, opening the fogges that we might see clearely, both where
        and in what danger we presently were, and also the way to escape: or els
        without faile we had ruinously runne vpon the rocks.
      </para>

      <para>
        When we knew perfectly our instant case, wee cast about to get againe on
        Sea bord, which (God be thanked) by night we obtained and praised God. The
        cleare continued scarce an houre, but the fogge fell againe as thicke as
        euer it was.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Warning pieces of safe passage discharged.</sidenote> Then the
        Rearadmirall and the Beare got themselues cleare without danger of yce and
        rocks, strooke their sailes and lay a hull, staying to haue the rest of the
        Fleet come forth: which as yet had not found the right way to cleare
        themselues from the danger of rockes and yce, vntill the next morning, at
        what time the Rearadmirall discharged certaine warning pieces to giue
        notice that she had escaped, and that the rest (by following of her) might
        set themselues free, which they did that day.
      </para>

      <para>
        Then hauing gathered our selues togither we proceeded on our purposed
        voyage, bearing off, and keeping our selues distant from the coast till the
        <date date="1578-07-19">19. day of Iuly</date>; at which time the fogges brake vp and dispersed, so that
        we might plainely and clearly behold the pleasant ayre, which so long had
        bene taken from vs, by the obscuritie of the foggie mists: and after that
        time we were not much incumbred therewith vntill we had left the confines
        of the Countrey.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>A faire sound betweene the Queenes foreland and Iackmans sound.</sidenote>
        Then we espying a fayre sound, supposed it to goe into <place>the Straights</place>
        betweene the <place>Queenes foreland</place> and <place>Iackmans sound</place>, which proued as we
        imagined. For <person>our Generall</person> sent forth againe the <ship>Gabriel </ship>to discouer it,
        who passed through with much difficulty: for there ran such an extreme
        current of a tide, with such a horrible gulfe, that with a fresh gale of
        wind they were scarce able to stemme it: yet at length with great trauaile
        they passed it, and came to <place>the Straights</place>, where they met with the <ship>Thomas
        Allen</ship>, the <ship>Thomas of Ipswich</ship>, and the <ship>Busse of Bridgewater</ship>: who altogether
        aduentured to beare into the yce againe, to see if they could obtaine their
        wished Port. But they were so incombred that with much difficultie they
        were able to get out againe, yet at the last they escaping, the <ship>Thomas
        Allen</ship>, and the <ship>Gabriel</ship> bare in with the Westerne shore, where they found
        harbour, and there moared their ships vntill the <date date="1578-08-04">fourth of August</date>, at which
        time they came to vs in the <place>Countesse of Warwicks sound</place>. The <ship>Thomas of
        Ipswich</ship> caught a great leake which caused her to cast againe to Seabord and
        so was mended.
      </para>

      <para>
        We sailed along still by the coast vntill we came to the <place>Queenes foreland</place>,
        at the point whereof we met with part of the gulfe aforesaid, which place
        or gulfe (as some of our Masters doe credibly report) doeth flow nine
        houres, and ebs but three. At that point wee discouered <place>certaine lands
        Southward</place>, which neither time nor opportunitie would serue to search. Then
        being come to <place>the mouth of the Straights</place>, we met with the <ship>Anne Francis</ship>, who
        had laine bulting vp and downe euer since her departure alone, neuer
        finding any of her company. We met then also the <ship>Francis of Foy</ship>, with whom
        againe we intended to venture and get in: but the yce was yet so thicke,
        that we were compelled againe to retyre and get vs on Sea bord.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>An horrible snowe fell in Iuly.</sidenote> There fell also the same day
        being the <date date="1578-07-26">26. of Iuly</date>, such an horrible snow, that it lay a foot thick vpon
        the hatches which frose as it fell.
      </para>

      <para>
        We had also at other times diuers cruell stormes both of snow and haile,
        which manifestly declared the distemperature of the Countrey: yet for all
        that wee were so many times repulsed and put backe from our purpose,
        knowing that lingering delay was not profitable for vs, but hurtfull to our
        voyage, we mutually consented to our valiant Generall once againe to giue
        the onset.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <date date="1578-07-28">28. day therefore of the same Iuly</date> we assayed, and with little trouble
        (God be praysed) we passed the dangers by day light. <sidenote>The time of
        our setting forward, &amp;c.</sidenote> Then night falling on the face of the earth, wee
        hulled in the cleare, til the chearefull light of the day had chased away
        the noysome darkenesse of the night: at which time we set forward towards
        our wished Port: by the <date date="1578-07-30">30. day</date> wee obteined our expected desire, where we
        found the <ship>Iudith</ship>, and the <ship>Michael</ship>: which brought no smal ioy vnto <person>the
        General</person>, and great consolation to the heauie hearts of those wearied
        wights.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <date date="1578-07-30">30. day of Iuly</date> we brought our ships into the <place>Countesse of Warwicks
        sound</place>, and moared them, namely these ships, The <ship>Admirall</ship>, the <ship>Rearadmirall</ship>,
        the <ship>Francis of Foy</ship>, the <ship>Beare Armenel</ship>, the <ship>Salomon</ship>, and the <ship>Busse of
        Bridgewater</ship>: which being done, <person>our Generall</person> commaunded vs all to come a
        shore vpon the <place>Countesses Iland</place>, where he set his Miners to worke vpon the
        Mine, giuing charge with expedition to dispatch with their lading.
      </para>

      <para>
        <person>Our Generall</person> himselfe, accompanied with his Gentlemen, diuers times made
        rodes into <place>sundry partes of the Countrey</place>, as well to finde new Mines, as
        also to finde out and see the people of the Countrey. <sidenote>The
        Countesse of Sussex Iland.</sidenote> He found out one Mine vpon an Island by <place>Beares
        sound</place>, and named it the <place>Countesse of Sussex Island</place>. <sidenote>Winters
        Fornace.</sidenote> One other was found in <place>Winters Fornace</place>, with diuers others, to
        which the ships were sent sunderly to be laden. <sidenote>Dauids Sound.</sidenote>
        In the same rodes he mette with diuers of the people of the Countrey at
        sundry times, as once at a place called <place>Dauids sound</place>: who shot at our men,
        and very desperately gaue them the onset, being not aboue three or foure in
        number, there being of our Countrey men aboue a dozen: but seeing
        themselues not able to preuaile, they tooke themselues to flight; whom our
        men pursued, but being not vsed to such craggie cliffes, they soone lost
        the sight of them, and so in vaine returned.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>The policie of the people for the safetie of themselues.</sidenote> We
        also saw of them at <place>Beares sound</place>, both by Sea and land in great companies:
        but they would at all times keepe the water betweene them and vs. And if
        any of our ships chanced to be in the sound (as they came diuers times,
        because the Harbor was not very good) the ship laded, and departed againe:
        then so long as any ships were in sight, the people would not be seene. But
        when as they perceiued the ships to be gone, they would not only shew
        themselues standing vpon high cliffes, and call vs to come ouer vnto them:
        but also would come in their Botes very neere to vs, as it were to brag at
        vs: whereof <person>our Generall</person> hauing aduertisement, sent for the Captaines and
        Gentlemen of the ships, to accompany and attend vpon him, with the Captaine
        also of the <ship>Anne Francis</ship>, who was but the night before come vnto vs. For
        they, and the <ship>Fleebote</ship> hauing lost vs the <date date="1578-07-26">26. day</date> in the great snow, put
        into an harbour in the <place>Queenes foreland</place>, where they found good Oare,
        wherewith they laded themselues, and came to seeke the Generall: so that
        now we had all our Shippes, sauing one Barke, which was lost, and the
        <ship>Thomas of Ipswich</ship>, who (compelled by what furie I knowe not) forsooke our
        company, and returned home without lading.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Their speedie flight at our Generalls arriual.</sidenote> <person>Our Generall</person>
        accompanied with his Gentlemen, (of whom I spake) came altogether to the
        <place>Countesse of Sussex Island</place>, neere to <place>Beares sound</place>: where he manned out
        certaine Pinasses, and went ouer to the people: who perceiuing his
        arriuall, fledde away with all speede, and in haste left certaine dartes
        and other engines behinde them, which we found: but the people we could not
        finde.
      </para>

      <para>
        The next morning <person>our Generall</person> perceiuing certaine of them in botes vpon the
        Sea gaue chase to them in a Pinnesse vnder saile, with a fresh gale of
        winde, but could by no meanes come neere vnto them: for the longer he
        sailed, the further off he was from them: which well shewed their cunning
        and actiuitie. Thus time wearing away, and the day of our departure
        approching, <person>our Generall</person> commaunded vs to lade with all expedition, that we
        might be againe <place>on Seaboard</place> with our ships: for whilest we were in the
        Countrey, we were in continual danger of freesing in: for often snowe and
        haile often falling, the water was so much frosen and congealed in the
        night, that in the morning we could scarce rowe our botes or Pinnesses,
        especially in <place>Diers sound</place>, which is a calme and still water: which caused
        our Generall to make the more haste, so that by the <date date="1578-08-30">30. day of August</date> we
        were all laden, and made all things ready to depart.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Gentlemen should haue inhabited the Countrey.</sidenote> But before I
        proceede any further herein, to shew what fortune befell at our departure,
        I will turne my penne a litle to <person>M. Captaine Fenton</person>, and those Gentlemen
        which should haue inhabited all the yeere in those Countries, whose valiant
        mindes were much to be commended: For doubtlesse they had done as they
        intended if lucke had not withstoode their willingnesse.
      </para>

      <para>
        For the Barke <ship>Dionyse</ship> which was lost, had in her much of their house which
        was prepared and should haue bene builded for them, with many other
        implements. Also the <ship>Thomas of Ipswich</ship> which had most of their prouision in
        her, came not into <place>the Streights</place> at all: neither did we see her since the
        day we were separated in the great snow, of which I spake before. For these
        causes, hauing not their house, nor yet prouision, they were disappointed
        of their pretence to tarie, and therefore laded their ships, and so came
        away with vs.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>An house tricked and garnished with diuers trinkets.</sidenote> But before
        we tooke shipping, we builded a litle house in the <place>Countesse of Warwicks
        Island</place>, and garnished it with many kinds of trifles, as Pinnes, Points,
        Laces, Glasses, Kombes, Babes on horsebacke and on foote, with innumerable
        other such fansies and toyes: thereby to allure and entice the people to
        some familiaritie against other yeeres.
      </para>

      <para>
        Thus hauing finished all things we departed the Countrey, as I sayd before:
        but because the <ship>Busse</ship> had not lading enough in her, she put into <place>Beares
        sound</place> to take in a little more. In the meane while the Admirall, and the
        rest without at Sea stayed for her. And that night fell such an outragious
        tempest, beating on our shipps with such vehement rigor, that anchor and
        cable auailed nought: for we were driuen on rockes and Islands of yce,
        insomuch that (had not the great goodnesse of God bene miraculously shewed
        to vs) we had bene cast away euery man. This danger was more doubtfull and
        terrible, then any that preceded or went before: for there was not any one
        shippe (I thinke) that escaped without damage. Some lost anchor and also
        cables, some botes, some Pinnesses: some anchor, cables, boates, and
        Pinnisses.
      </para>

      <para>
        This boystrous storme so seuered vs from one another, that one shippe knewe
        not what was become of another. The Admirall knewe not where to finde the
        <ship>Viceadmirall</ship> or <ship>Rearadmirall</ship>, or any other ship of our company. Our
        Generall being on land in Beares sound could not come to his shippe, but
        was compelled to goe aboord the Gabriel where he continued all the way
        homeward: for the boystrous blasts continued so extreamely and so long a
        time, that they sent vs homewarde (which was Gods fauour towardes vs) will
        we, nill we, in such haste as not any one of vs were able to keepe in
        company with other, but were separated. And if by chance any one Shippe did
        ouertake other, by swiftnesse of sayle, or mette, as they often did: yet
        was the rigour of the wind so hidious, that they could not continue company
        together the space of one whole night.
      </para>

      <para>
        <sidenote>Our entring the coastes dangerous.</sidenote> Thus our iourney outward was
        not so pleasant, but our comming thither, entering the coasts and countrey,
        by <place>narrow Streights</place>, perillous yce, and swift tides, our times of aboade
        there in snowe and stormes, and our departure from thence the <date date="1578-08-31">31. of August</date>
        with dangerous blustering windes and tempests, which that night arose, was
        as vncomfortable: separating vs so as we sayled, that not any of vs mette
        together, vntill the <date date="1578-09-28">28. of September</date>, which day we fell on the English
        coastes, betweene <place>Sylley</place> and the <place>landes ende</place>, and passed the channell,
        vntill our arriuall in the <place>riuer of Thames</place>.
      </para>
  </extract>
</extracts>